[Music]
Good day everybody. I hope you're all
keeping well. It's a really exciting day
today for a number of reasons. I get to
break bread with a with a very good
friend of mine, Ashad um Kaval who's
done some amazing work that we're going
to talk through um and hopefully some of
the richness of this conversation will
really come to the four. My name is
Jason Aard and I've been very fortunate
to do work in the areas of race and the
intersection. But most importantly, I'm
going to be talking to a very dear
friend today. Arshad, I would be
extremely grateful and privileged if you
could introduce yourself, your work, and
where we're kind of where how we ended
up here really in the first instance.
Absolutely. Uh first of all, hi Jason as
always as always. It's really lovely to
see you, to meet with you, to talk with
you, and to talk real, right? Which is
what this is all about, to talk real.
Um, so my name is Harshed Kaval, and uh
I'm currently a lecturer in social
sciences, but I've kind of um I've been
around in academia and outside academia
for a long time now. And it's that long
time really, which the book is really
about. It's about the the fabric that
gets woven and interwoven into our
lives. It gets woven into our social,
psychological, emotional mechanisms of
everyday meaning making. And I guess in
many ways um they say write what you
know. And I guess that's what this book
really is about. It's about writing
about something which I felt,
experienced and then observed and
listened and witnessed lots of things
around me which I felt were important to
talk about in real terms.
That's brilliant. It's absolutely
brilliant. I'll show that. One of the
things that I'm really intrigued in or
intrigued with, sorry, is the title. How
did you come up with the title and what
was some of the thinking behind that?
Sure. Um, yeah, that's a really good
question. And it the title originally
was it was a choice of two titles. And
one title was actually to call the book
um by the name of the thing that I
really talk about in the book, which is
this twoword phrase, white narcissist.
Um and the book the book's title as it
is whiteness racial trauma and
university I think better encapsulates
and has a better reach in terms of
connecting to people and that is really
principally about connecting to
experiences. Very often people say what
what can you summarize what this book's
about in one sentence? And I've been so
reluctant and unable actually I don't
think I'm I'm articulate enough a lot of
the time to be able to do that. But over
the past few months I've gone back to
why I started the book and that's given
me a root into the
oneliner. The book really is the
discussions that take place when
whiteness leaves the room.
So when there is an opportunity to talk
with honesty, with uh experience, with
the felt lived reality of what we've all
experienced in so many different ways,
that is whiteness. And when whiteness
can't be articulated, identified, and
then unraveled actually for its impact
and for its insiduous nature, we end up
with harm, which is a form of trauma.
And this for me I think I I articulate
it as racial trauma. And racial trauma
is a term that never gets used in the
university system in educational
contexts. And yet harm is real, racisms
are real. And the university is a
principal site at which on which these
harms get produced. So that's where the
title really comes from. Really Jason. I
really I really love that Arshad. I
mean, one of the things that you kind of
speak about which is a a recurrent
tenant. It's almost a spine of the trice
is the white narcissist bit. Could you
just unpack that for people that will be
engaging with this will be listening?
You know, as far as I'm aware, I haven't
heard of that term before. So, I would
credit you with, you know, um the
development of the term. So, what does
that mean for people who will be
listening in and who might be using who
may be able to use that as um a proxy to
explain their experiences with
whiteness?
Sure. Um, and I I've been very kind of
I've been very careful and cognizant
about the term white narcissist because
it has lots of implications and
underpinnings from, you know,
psychoanalytic and psychological
therapeutic work, clinical psychological
formulations of narcissistic
personalities, etc.
For me, I've I've been very careful to
say I'm not talking about an individual
psychological structure, but rather what
I'm trying to do is I think something
that we all do really, which is make
sense of this very real uh effective
thing, right? It's it's inside us. We
feel it. We experience it. We observe it
in in schools, in in classrooms, in uh
boardroom meetings, and in lecture
theaters. We observe it in the canteen
in the cafeteria but we can't quite make
sense of it. The literature and the
research has very very um you know in a
very rich way talked about whiteness and
whiteness grammar whiteness systems
um and but for me there was something
missing from that. it needed an add-on.
And every time I thought about what I
had experienced and what other
colleagues had experienced, there was
something about narcissism inside
structures, inside
institutions. Now for me certainly when
I'm talking about white narcissistic
structures, I am talking about
individuals. I am talking about people
who take um agency. They make decisions
about what kinds of norms and values and
and cultures of harm or cultures of what
you know Charles Mills talks about
militant ignorance. These are individual
actions which when aggregated when
formulated inside relations of power
actually then cascade these these
systems that are fundamentally
narcissistic. And by that what I mean is
narcissism requires a constant
reproduction of its own idealized image
bounced back to it. And so when I'm when
I'm observing the university over the
past few years, what I'm seeing is a
constant reperformance and a constant
reinforcement of imagery of particular
types of words, particular types of
positive uh facads which make it look
like a very beautiful uh liberal
equalitybased system that sits outside
of all the the rough stuff that happens
in society.
In actual fact, you dig deep enough, if
we are able to give ourselves the time
to think critically enough about these
things, it's fundamentally narcissistic,
which means the system is run through
narcissism and requires individuals to
take often
decisions which require that
narcissistic whiteness to be there all
the time. And that fundamentally
excludes anyone. We can define people of
color, racially minoritized people, but
anyone who doesn't reflect back what the
system requires for it to replenish
itself. And so that for me is white
narcissists.
I really appreciate that explanation and
you know many readers of this book will
also appreciate that including you know
um allies of the sort as well.
One of the things that I'm really
intrigued in and I guess you know I I
could lay claim to saying that you you
I'm very fortunate to be able to call
you a friend and from a I guess a friend
perspective and having some
understanding of you know how you've
traversed these you know this this kind
of really thorny terrain in terms of
higher education and the racial
inequality and discrimination that
happens within it. I'm really intrigued
to know how much of you is in these
pages. How much of you makes up the
words that are on this page or how much
of it is just a general experience that
yes comprises some of your experience
but speaks to the wider diaspor diaspora
in terms of people who make up the
academy that are ethnic minority.
That's a really interesting question,
Jason, that um I can always rely on you
on asking those questions that make me
pause and think, and I really appreciate
that. Um it's both. On the one hand, I
would say, um it's 100% me because I
think I saw this book as an opportunity
to to breathe, to pause at a moment when
there wasn't much pausing going on. So
over the past few years and this is
especially
since you know the resurgence of Black
Lives Matter, the statues toppling,
decolonized my curriculum, why is my
curriculum white, all these major
programs of change instigated by many
students around the world who were
asking very powerful
questions. Just at this time I started
observing institutions
um producing the machinery of movement
where suddenly everybody was
anti-racist. Suddenly everyone was
decolonizing everything and you know we
can kind of we we you know you yourself
have written about this in very powerful
ways as have many other colleagues. What
does it actually mean? What does it lead
to? How is the problem being formulated
and conceptualized and by who?
So there was very little time for pause
and to think what actually is going on
and what questions are not being asked.
And so the pausing, the breathing, the
taking stock both of the situation but
also of my position in it. You know, I
write very very candidly, very honestly
in the book that, you know, in many ways
this book um it signposts my
relationship to the academy which has
been really really problematic in the
sense that there's always a scrabbling
around and a trying to chase
affirmation, adulation, acceptance. you
know, if only we work harder, if only we
um adopt the norms and the values and
the and the mechanisms for success that
the academy deems valuable, then maybe
we'll get promoted, you know, then we'll
get acceptance. And it gave me a chance
to think about these things critically
for me. And that required having a very
uh uh having a thought about what my
need in the moment is. and my need in
the moment as I think actually it always
has been is the fullest creative
expression of myself. So everything of
me is in the book. But I think usefully
the things I talk about in the book as I
as I'm getting feedback from people from
different bits of the world who are
reading the book saying, do you know I
could apply this stuff to lots of other
institutions. I could apply it to what
goes on in healthcare, what goes on in
business management, what goes on in
other parts of the education system. And
suddenly people are seeing resonances
inside their conversations with other
people outside of work. So it's a it's a
long answer to your very powerful short
question, but yeah, I think it's both.
It it's it's completely me and it's
about the wider diaspora of experiences
out there.
Ash, I really appreciate that
particularly in relation to the wider
diaspora of experiences out there. And
one of the things that I'm also really
intrigued to kind of learn is that we
are living in a state of high societal
and political turbulence where actually
a lot of this work you know the the is
being infringed upon. You know our
liberties are being infringed upon. the
eglletarian ideals that we hold so dear
being infringed upon and the relevance
of anti-racist work has been completely
dismissed um here across the pond and
across the world generally speaking at
this moment as we find ourselves over
the last two decades leaning heavily to
the right. What I'm kind of intrigued to
know is how does this book steady what
is steady that turbulence
and how has it been received because in
these really difficult times now this
work becomes even the pecarity of
individuals producing such amazing work
like yourself becomes even more
difficult um to put your head above the
parapit so to speak.
Yeah, the I agree Jason and it's I think
it's really interesting that you raised
this this aspect of contemporary the
contemporary landscape. I think in many
ways what we're seeing is a is a
particular moment in time when things
are um they're appearing in
consciousness much more. They're in
social media, they're in the news,
they're everywhere. this stuff that
people like us do in various levels
around race and DEI
um doesn't seem to have any relevance
anymore because it's been kind of you
know it's been pushed out of the the
mainstream now there's no need for it. I
think if anything um a book like this
and other books that do similar kinds of
work maybe using different formulations
um are of course even more important now
than ever because I think we do need to
continue the vigilance in systems like
education systems, higher education,
university systems because if we don't
keep up the vigilance
then all the gains that we may have made
over the past 20, 30, 40 years end up
being lost and we end up with another
blank page. And of course, if that blank
page of equality and meritocracy is
fundamentally defined by, you know,
majority white systems and white players
and white senior management, then we're
in big trouble because we keep on having
to reinvent the wheel
about compassion, humanity, equality,
anti-racism. So, I think I think there
is there is an increased vicarity right
now. And you know I I've been kind of
doing this for for quite a few decades
and I consider myself as a as I speak
from a position of privilege to be able
to say these words to write these words
without too much fear of of backlash
although I'm sure you know these these
kinds of ideas if they're taken up by
various groups in society they can
certainly target anyone but um I think
there is a precarity um and I think as I
you know I say towards the end of the
book which we can kind of talk about in
a bit but I do say
that we need to keep
on championing a change in the system.
So the university systems are really
characterized by the very people who
have been marginalized in the first
place and excluded. You know, all those
people whose voices never appear in the
policy documents, who never appear in
the promotional literature, whose voices
never really appear as legitimate bodies
and minds, they're the voices we're
going to keep on creating solidarity
networks with, for, and through. And
through that, even precarious moments
like this, well, they'll kind of they'll
calm down. You know, there's there's
enough of us, and I say in the book,
we're not going anywhere. We're going to
continue writing and resisting and
teaching and being compassionate with
each other because this is I think where
the power is. You know there's two
things and it's the penultimate question
but you spoke about compassion. One
thing that reflects back in these pages
in, you know, that there's almost a
paradox in some respects is the absence
of compassion for people of color in the
academy. And then the need and then the
need for compassion in the academy in
terms of making it a racially inclusive
space and allowing people of color to be
able to land in those spaces without
fear of marginalization, victimization
or systemic
violence. Could you just talk to me
about compassion and how you've
conceptualized it in this book and the
practice in terms of how you engage with
this concept on a day-to-day basis? cuz
I would I I would say you're one of the
most compassionate people I've come
across in the sector and it's not a
given that people are compassionate
actually. I would say I could probably
count on less than seven fingers how
many compassionate people I've met in
the sector. So how do you conceptualize
it within the book and then how is it
lived out in your practice as an
academic and a practitioner?
Yeah, that's a really Yeah, that's a I
mean, I like I like the word compassion,
but it's so full of different layers,
isn't it? Layers of of what we're able
to mobilize in any given moment. Uh
layers of what we can't mobilize for
fear of security or lack of security for
our positions. I think
um I think compassion with each other
inside you know what has been classed as
the neoliberal uh marketization of the
intellectual and academic endeavor. I
think compassion is the only answer
there is to a problem that won't even be
conceptualized properly. In other words,
compassion is the answer to the question
that hasn't been asked. you know uh you
know in in any kind of in any system
that sits outside of the the key
performance indicate machinery the
mechanics of
extraction any system that sits outside
this that fundamentally relies on each
other's kindness so that we could all
rise together we can all help each other
I think that is the only solution there
is and that can only happen when we can
talk to each other. We can connect with
each other and we can create our own
spaces. Now, people have said, well, how
how do you do you see these spaces
sitting inside the system? Because if
they do, you've got to ask questions
about how much compromise is needed and
what gets lost or are these spaces
sitting outside? And for me, it's both.
It's always going to be both. There is
always going to be losses and gains
whichever decision one makes. But I
think compassion is the key to radical
justice. It's it's in the writings of
all the global southern decolonial
critical writers of the past 100 150 200
years. It's in the words of writers like
yourself and all the other contemporary
academics and writers. Compassion needs
to be the key because something that
really came across and you know Jason
you will have seen this that in part of
the book in at the end of the chapter
white narcissus there's a poem and I lay
out very clearly why I've done this.
It's because this notion of white
narcissus
arrived to me as an invitation and it
was two words that haunted me for 6
months. I had no idea what they meant or
where they came from. But I did know
that my body and my emotions were
speaking to me in a language that my
mind couldn't yet understand, but my
creative expression attempted to
interpret. And so the poetry that rolls
out of the two words white
narcissists really accurately explains
my experience of whiteness in the
academy. And I think from what I've
heard from other people, it seems to
resonate their experiences too. So I
think the narcissistic whiteness
structures that I speak about in the
book are fundamentally devoid of
compassion and that itself is something
that comes out of I like you know if you
like colonial racial history of
whiteness you know there is a
fundamental brutality to how these
systems work. So I guess I'm speaking to
the need to go back to what we know best
which is that human compassionate need
to connect with each other.
I think that's beautiful and I and I you
know and it's difficult because academia
is a space that is bereft of that kind
of compassion and actually society is a
microcosm you know you know universities
or the academy are microcosm of society
and so it's only reflecting what we have
um as a point of navigation in society
unfortunately so that is really really
powerful to the final question then I
guess you know in terms of the book and
the kind of take-home message. If I was
to kind of ask you to summarize the book
in kind of three powerful take-home
messages, how would you summarize this
for people currently reading, people who
are going to be future readers? What are
the kind of take-home messages? Because
it's a book that's so rich that can
speak to so many different experiences
in terms of race against the
intersection. Um, and you know, as
someone that's actively engaged in your
work, there's something in it for
everyone who engages in this work and it
will strengthen their resolve. So, for
me, I'm really intrigued to hear your
three take-h home messages for the book
in terms of how we orientate forward.
It's going to be a tough call, Jason,
but I'll I'll try. Um there's a section
at the end where I I I place the
epilogue and it's called the subtitle is
you know writing yourself in and out of
the text. Um for me I think asking who
do we who do we write for and
why is really really important because I
think that becomes a key question. Who
are we doing the work for? If we're in a
if we're in the academy and we're trying
to work our way through the system, who
is it for and what compromises and
losses are made in that process?
The second thing I think is ask the
questions that haven't been asked about
systems and structures of white
narcissism because when we start to
formulate and articulate this particular
thread that's when the imagery and the
psychology and the emotional faculties
kick in our I think I really firmly
believe that our bodies have an
intelligence that can really help in
these situations because it's our bodies
and our minds that take the brunt of
what race and racism does. And of
course, as I write in the book, racism's
attempt to dismantle you from the inside
out. So, let's figure out what it is
that these white narcissist narcissistic
systems look like, how they work, and we
need to point them out and call them out
whenever we can.
Thirdly,
connection. It's always going to be
connection with each other. We've got to
reach out to each other. We've got to
talk to each other. And we've got to
create the spaces where we can talk
about the things that we can talk about
when whiteness leaves the room. And you
mentioned allies before. And yeah, I do
believe in this. I think without
allyship, you know, it's it's so much
harder. Um, and I'm including our allies
in this. Our allies can talk with us,
can learn through us and with us. They
can learn for us. But it's going to be
their journey, their burden too.
So I guess there's three take-home
messages. Number one, ask who are we
doing this for and what compromises,
losses and gains uh that might
accumulate and the impact on our minds
and bodies. Uh number two, we can point
to systems of white narcissistic
structures because they are everywhere
and they are fundamental a part of
racial colonial history. And number
three, we've got to connect with each
other and keep on connecting and
creating our spaces.
Dr. Arshad Caval, I just want to say
it's been an absolute privilege to break
bread with you. I can't emphasize enough
and I'm slightly biased but I do have
the occasional ability to be objective
that I do think this is a wonderful
contribution to knowledge but more
importantly a movement that really
requires galvanizing reorganizing and
restructuring in the face in the ever
changing face of the racisms that we
face. So just thank you so much for your
contribution to this space. Thank you
for your existence and thank you for
your perseverance. It's a beautiful
amazing book that's powerfully written
and within the pages there is something
there for everyone to take from that. So
thank you Ash and as the custom would go
the last word goes to you. So is there
anything you'd like to say to
prospective readers also that will be
reading this book to bear in mind
possibly.
uh all all I can say to prospective
readers is uh read engage but do so with
a real sense of pause and space. I
didn't write in one week or one month. I
I wrote with a great deal of uh pauses
and starts and fits and lurches because
I took time to think through what it was
I need to do. So I would imagine people
read it at their own pace, but to take
time and to pause with it and to allow
it to sit and land uh and from their
discussions, it's only ever going to be
a springboard to more people doing more
of this wonderful work. And thank you,
Jason, as always. Um it's really great
to speak to you. Um thank you for your
ongoing support. It was, you know, your
amazing invitation to to be a part of
this fantastic series. So, it's a real
honor to have had this journey, had the
opportunity, uh the commissioning
editor, Delena, and of course, Sage or
all the people behind the behind the
behind the background actually who who
do so much amazing work to make this
happen. So, yeah, I'm very honored. I'm
very grateful.
[Music]